<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<References xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema http://beta.iedb.org/schema/Curation.xsd" xmlns="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <Reference>
        <ReferenceId>1066</ReferenceId>
        <DateLastUpdated>2018-10-16-07:00</DateLastUpdated>
        <Article>
            <PubmedId>14962388</PubmedId>
            <Abstract>Mycoplasma arthritidis-derived mitogen (MAM) is a superantigen that can activate large fractions of T cells bearing particular TCR Vbeta elements. Here we report the crystal structure of MAM complexed with a major histocompatibility complex (MHC) antigen, HLA-DR1, loaded with haemagglutinin peptide 306-318 (HA). The structure reveals that MAM has a novel fold composed of two alpha-helical domains. This fold is entirely different from that of the pyrogenic superantigens, consisting of a beta-grasped motif and a beta barrel. In the complex, the N-terminal domain of MAM binds orthogonally to the MHC alpha1 domain and the bound HA peptide, and to a lesser extent to the MHC beta1 domain. Two MAM molecules form an asymmetric dimer and cross-link two MHC antigens to form a plausible, dimerized MAM-MHC complex. These data provide the first crystallographic evidence that superantigens can dimerize MHC molecules. Based on our structure, a model of the TCR2MAM2MHC2 complex is proposed.</Abstract>
            <ArticleYear>2004</ArticleYear>
            <ArticlePages>277-88</ArticlePages>
            <ArticleTitle>Crystal structure of Mycoplasma arthritidis mitogen complexed with HLA-DR1 reveals a novel superantigen fold and a dimerized superantigen-MHC complex.</ArticleTitle>
            <Authors>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Zhao</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Yiwei</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Li</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Zhong</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Drozd</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Sandra J</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Guo</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Yi</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Mourad</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Walid</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Li</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Hongmin</ForeName>
                </Author>
            </Authors>
            <Affiliations>Wadsworth Center, New York State Department of Health, Empire State Plaza, PO Box 509, Albany, NY 12201, USA.</Affiliations>
            <ArticleChemicalList>Antigens;Antigens, Bacterial;HLA-DR1 Antigen;Mitogens;Mycoplasma arthritidis mitogen;Proteins;Superantigens</ArticleChemicalList>
            <ArticleMeshHeadingsList>Antigens; Antigens, Bacterial; Crystallography, X-Ray; Dimerization; HLA-DR1 Antigen(chemistry); Major Histocompatibility Complex(physiology); Mitogens(chemistry); Models, Molecular; Mycoplasma arthritidis(metabolism); Protein Folding; Protein Structure, Tertiary; Proteins; Superantigens(chemistry)</ArticleMeshHeadingsList>
            <Journal>
                <Volume>12</Volume>
                <Issue>2</Issue>
                <Title>Structure (London, England)</Title>
                <Issn>0969-2126</Issn>
                <MedlineTa>Structure</MedlineTa>
            </Journal>
        </Article>
        <Epitopes>
            <Epitope>
                <EpitopeName>HA (306-318)</EpitopeName>
                <EpitopeStructure>
                    <FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                        <ChemicalType>Peptide from protein</ChemicalType>
                        <LinearSequence>PKYVKQNTLKLAT</LinearSequence>
                        <StartingPosition>306</StartingPosition>
                        <EndingPosition>318</EndingPosition>
                        <SourceMolecule>
                            <GenBankId>0704243A</GenBankId>
                        </SourceMolecule>
                        <SourceOrganismId>11320</SourceOrganismId>
                    </FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                </EpitopeStructure>
                <LocationOfData>Experimental procedures</LocationOfData>
                <EpitopeId>48237</EpitopeId>
                <ReferenceStartingPosition>306</ReferenceStartingPosition>
                <ReferenceEndingPosition>318</ReferenceEndingPosition>
                <EpitopeEvidenceCode>Representative selection</EpitopeEvidenceCode>
                <EpitopeStructureDefines>Exact Epitope</EpitopeStructureDefines>
                <Assays>
                    <MhcBinding>
                        <LocationOfData>Figures 1, 2, 4, Tables 1, 2 and PDB 1R5I</LocationOfData>
                        <MhcBindingId>1489174</MhcBindingId>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>175</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <QuantitativeMeasurement>2.6</QuantitativeMeasurement>
                            <MeasurementInequality>=</MeasurementInequality>
                            <AssayComments>The crystal structure contains the MHC/epitope complex bound to the superantigen (SAG) Mycoplasma arthritidis-derived mitogen (MAM). SAG PDB chain is D (and H). There are two SAG/MHC/Epitope complexes in the asymmetrical unit. The two SAG molecules interact and form an asymmetrical dimer through their C-terminal domains, cross-linking the two MHC/Epitope complexes. The analysis was based on the first complex, but the results are also applicable to the second complex. Residues that had a well ordered electron density and were included in the final model are: MHC chain α (PDB chain A) residues 1-181; MHC chain β (PDB chain B) residues 1-190; epitope (PDB chain C) residues 306-318; SAG (PDB chain D) residues 1-213.</AssayComments>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <MhcAlleleId>52</MhcAlleleId>
                        <ThreeDimensionalStructureOfComplex>
                            <ComplexPdbId>1R5I</ComplexPdbId>
                            <MhcChain1PdbChain>A</MhcChain1PdbChain>
                            <MhcChain2PdbChain>B</MhcChain2PdbChain>
                            <EpitopePdbChain>C</EpitopePdbChain>
                            <EpitopeResidues>C: P306, K307, Y308, V309, K310, Q311, N312, T313, L314, K315, L316, A317, T318;</EpitopeResidues>
                            <ViewerFlag>Y</ViewerFlag>
                            <Comments>[| P-2: P306; P-1: K307; P1: Y308; P2: V309; P3: K310; P4: Q311; P5: N312; P6: T313; P7: L314; P8: K315; P9: L316; P10: A317; P11: T318; |] The SAG molecule interacts with the MHC in the region between β1 and β2 strands and between β3 and β4 strands of the α-chain, with the α1 helix of the α-chain and with the β1 helix of the β-chain. Also the SAG contacts the central part of the epitope, from residue P3: K310; to P8: K315; . No major conformational changes were observed on the MHC molecule and the epitope, upon binding of the SAG molecule to the MHC/epitope complex. The only apparent difference is a change in the side chain conformation of epitope residue P5: N312.</Comments>
                            <CuratedContacts>
                                <EpitopeResidues>C: P306, K307, Y308, V309, K310, Q311, N312, T313, L314, K315, L316, A317, T318;</EpitopeResidues>
                                <EpitopeResiduesInteractingWithMhc>C: ;</EpitopeResiduesInteractingWithMhc>
                                <MhcResiduesInteractingWithEpitope>A: ; B: ;</MhcResiduesInteractingWithEpitope>
                            </CuratedContacts>
                            <CalculatedContacts>
                                <EpitopeResiduesInteractingWithMhc>C: P306, K307, Y308, V309, K310, Q311, N312, T313, L314, K315, L316, A317, T318</EpitopeResiduesInteractingWithMhc>
                                <MhcResiduesInteractingWithEpitope>A: Q9, E11, F24, I31, W43, F51, A52, S53, F54, E55, G58, N62, V65, D66, N69, I72, R76; B: W9, L11, F13, Y47, P56, D57, Y60, W61, L67, Q70, R71, A74, T77, Y78, H81, N82, V85, G86, F89</MhcResiduesInteractingWithEpitope>
                                <ContactAreaForEpitope>1308.0</ContactAreaForEpitope>
                                <ContactAreaForMhc>947.2</ContactAreaForMhc>
                            </CalculatedContacts>
                        </ThreeDimensionalStructureOfComplex>
                    </MhcBinding>
                </Assays>
            </Epitope>
        </Epitopes>
    </Reference>
</References>

