<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<References xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema http://beta.iedb.org/schema/Curation.xsd" xmlns="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <Reference>
        <ReferenceId>1073</ReferenceId>
        <DateLastUpdated>2020-09-10-07:00</DateLastUpdated>
        <Article>
            <PubmedId>12051920</PubmedId>
            <Abstract>While most immunotherapies for cancer have focused on eliciting specific CD8+ cytotoxic T lymphocyte killing of tumor cells, a mounting body of evidence suggests that stimulation of anti-tumor CD4+ T cell help may be required for highly effective therapy. Several MHC class II-restricted tumor antigens that specifically activate such CD4+ helper T lymphocytes have now been identified, including one from a melanoma tumor that is caused by a single base-pair mutation in the glycolytic enzyme triosephosphate isomerase. This mutation results in the conversion of a threonine residue to isoleucine within the antigenic epitope, concomitant with a greater than five log-fold increase in stimulation of a CD4+ tumor-infiltrating lymphocyte line. Here, we present the crystal structures of HLA-DR1 in complex with both wild-type and mutant TPI peptide antigens, the first structures of tumor peptide antigen/MHC class II complexes recognized by CD4+ T cells to be reported. These structures show that very minor changes in the binding surface for T cell receptor correspond to the dramatic differences in T cell stimulation. Defining the structural basis by which CD4+ T cell help is invoked in an anti-tumor immune response will likely aid the design of more effective cancer immunotherapies.</Abstract>
            <ArticleYear>2002</ArticleYear>
            <ArticlePages>449-61</ArticlePages>
            <ArticleTitle>Minor structural changes in a mutated human melanoma antigen correspond to dramatically enhanced stimulation of a CD4+ tumor-infiltrating lymphocyte line.</ArticleTitle>
            <Authors>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Sundberg</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Eric J</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Sawicki</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Mark W</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Southwood</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Scott</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Andersen</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Peter S</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Sette</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Alessandro</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Mariuzza</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Roy A</ForeName>
                </Author>
            </Authors>
            <Affiliations>Center for Advanced Research in Biotechnology, W. M. Keck Laboratory for Structural Biology, University of Maryland Biotechnology Institute, 9600 Gudelsky Drive, Rockville, MD 20850, USA. sundberg@umbi.umd.edu</Affiliations>
            <ArticleChemicalList>Antigens;HLA-DR1 Antigen;Peptide Fragments;Receptors, Antigen, T-Cell;Triose-Phosphate Isomerase</ArticleChemicalList>
            <ArticleMeshHeadingsList>Amino Acid Sequence; Antigen Presentation; Antigens(chemistry; genetics; immunology); CD4-Positive T-Lymphocytes(cytology; immunology); Crystallography, X-Ray; HLA-DR1 Antigen(chemistry; immunology); Humans; Lymphocyte Activation; Melanoma(immunology); Models, Molecular; Molecular Sequence Data; Mutation(genetics); Peptide Fragments(chemistry; genetics; immunology); Protein Conformation; Receptors, Antigen, T-Cell(chemistry; immunology); Triose-Phosphate Isomerase(chemistry; genetics; immunology)</ArticleMeshHeadingsList>
            <Journal>
                <Volume>319</Volume>
                <Issue>2</Issue>
                <Title>Journal of molecular biology</Title>
                <Issn>1089-8638</Issn>
                <MedlineTa>J Mol Biol</MedlineTa>
            </Journal>
        </Article>
        <Epitopes>
            <Epitope>
                <EpitopeName>TPI(mut) (23-37)</EpitopeName>
                <EpitopeStructure>
                    <SequenceMoleculeNoNaturalSource>
                        <ChemicalType>Peptide, no natural source</ChemicalType>
                        <LinearSequence>GELIGILNAAKVPAD</LinearSequence>
                    </SequenceMoleculeNoNaturalSource>
                </EpitopeStructure>
                <EpitopeRelatedObject>
                    <RelatedObjectType>The epitope is an analog of:</RelatedObjectType>
                    <RelatedObject>
                        <FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                            <ChemicalType>Peptide from protein</ChemicalType>
                            <LinearSequence>GELIGTLNAAKVPAD</LinearSequence>
                            <StartingPosition>23</StartingPosition>
                            <EndingPosition>37</EndingPosition>
                            <SourceMolecule>
                                <GenBankId>NP_000356.1</GenBankId>
                            </SourceMolecule>
                            <SourceOrganismId>9606</SourceOrganismId>
                        </FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                    </RelatedObject>
                </EpitopeRelatedObject>
                <LocationOfData>Figure 2</LocationOfData>
                <EpitopeId>79835</EpitopeId>
                <EpitopeStructureDefines>Exact Epitope</EpitopeStructureDefines>
                <EpitopeComments>The epitope is an analog of the wild-type TPI and has a mutation: T28 -&gt; I28.</EpitopeComments>
                <Assays>
                    <MhcBinding>
                        <LocationOfData>Figures 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, Tables 1, 2 and PDB 1KLG</LocationOfData>
                        <MhcBindingId>1489400</MhcBindingId>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>175</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <QuantitativeMeasurement>2.4</QuantitativeMeasurement>
                            <MeasurementInequality>=</MeasurementInequality>
                            <AssayComments>The crystal structure contains the MHC/epitope complex bound to the superantigen (SAG) staphylococcal enterotoxin type C3, variant 3B2 (SEC3-3B2). SAG PDB chain is D.</AssayComments>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <MhcAlleleId>52</MhcAlleleId>
                        <ThreeDimensionalStructureOfComplex>
                            <ComplexPdbId>1KLG</ComplexPdbId>
                            <MhcChain1PdbChain>A</MhcChain1PdbChain>
                            <MhcChain2PdbChain>B</MhcChain2PdbChain>
                            <EpitopePdbChain>C</EpitopePdbChain>
                            <EpitopeResidues>C: G23, E24, L25, I26, G27, I28, L29, N30, A31, A32, K33, V34, P35, A36, D37;</EpitopeResidues>
                            <ViewerFlag>Y</ViewerFlag>
                            <Comments>[| P-3: G23; P-2: E24; P-1: L25; P1: I26; P2: G27; P3: I28; P4: L29; P5: N30; P6: A31; P7: A32; P8: K33; P9: V34; P10: P35; P11: A36; P12: D37; |]  The SAG molecule interacts with regions of the MHC α subunit, outside of the epitope binding groove and does not contact the epitope. As such, the binding of the SAG to the MHC/Epitope complex does not cause any conformational changes to the epitope structure. Only some information is given about MHC-Epitope interactions. Epitope residue P3: I28 makes extensive interactions with the MHC α subunit, including van der Waals interactions with A: Q9, F22, F54, G58, N62. Conformational comparison between complexes SEC3-3B2/HLA-DR1 with TPI(T28-&gt;I28), SEC3-3B2/HLA-DR1 with TPI(wt) [PDB: 1KLU] and SEC3-3B2/HLA-DR1 with HA [unpublished data]: The first two structures show very little structural deviation from one another. No significant differences were found between the two MHC molecules. The structures of the two epitopes are also very similar. Most differences are found at their N and C-terminal residues: P-3: G23 and P12: D37. The only important difference between TPI(wt) and TPI(T28-&gt;I28) is at the side chain of P3: I28 in the mutant epitope, which is rotated relative to that of residue P3: T28 in the wild-type epitope. In all three structures, the epitopes have similar main-chain conformations, especially in the region spanning the epitope anchor residues P1, P4, P6, P7, P9. The only difference is that epitope HA binds to the MHC molecule with a slightly higher affinity than the other two. This is because of the different interactions the residues make at position P4. Specifically, residue P4: L29 in TPI makes three van der Waals interactions with residues from the MHC α-chain, whereas residue P4: T313; in HA, apart form these three van der Waals interactions, also makes a hydrogen bond with an MHC α-chain residue and water-mediated hydrogen bonds to two other MHC α-chain residues.</Comments>
                            <CuratedContacts>
                                <EpitopeResidues>C: G23, E24, L25, I26, G27, I28, L29, N30, A31, A32, K33, V34, P35, A36, D37;</EpitopeResidues>
                                <EpitopeResiduesInteractingWithMhc>C: ;</EpitopeResiduesInteractingWithMhc>
                                <MhcResiduesInteractingWithEpitope>A: ; B: ;</MhcResiduesInteractingWithEpitope>
                            </CuratedContacts>
                            <CalculatedContacts>
                                <EpitopeResiduesInteractingWithMhc>C: G23, E24, L25, I26, G27, I28, L29, N30, A31, A32, K33, V34, P35, D37</EpitopeResiduesInteractingWithMhc>
                                <MhcResiduesInteractingWithEpitope>A: Q9, F22, F24, F51, A52, S53, F54, E55, G58, A59, N62, V65, D66, N69, I72, K75; B: L11, F13, P56, D57, Y60, W61, R71, Y78, H81, N82, V85</MhcResiduesInteractingWithEpitope>
                                <ContactAreaForEpitope>1289.2</ContactAreaForEpitope>
                                <ContactAreaForMhc>960.4</ContactAreaForMhc>
                            </CalculatedContacts>
                        </ThreeDimensionalStructureOfComplex>
                    </MhcBinding>
                </Assays>
                <Assays>
                    <MhcBinding>
                        <LocationOfData>Table 3</LocationOfData>
                        <MhcBindingId>1907126</MhcBindingId>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>417</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <QuantitativeMeasurement>25.0</QuantitativeMeasurement>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <MhcAlleleId>52</MhcAlleleId>
                    </MhcBinding>
                </Assays>
            </Epitope>
            <Epitope>
                <EpitopeName>TPI (23-37)</EpitopeName>
                <EpitopeStructure>
                    <FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                        <ChemicalType>Peptide from protein</ChemicalType>
                        <LinearSequence>GELIGTLNAAKVPAD</LinearSequence>
                        <StartingPosition>23</StartingPosition>
                        <EndingPosition>37</EndingPosition>
                        <SourceMolecule>
                            <GenBankId>NP_000356.1</GenBankId>
                        </SourceMolecule>
                        <SourceOrganismId>9606</SourceOrganismId>
                    </FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                </EpitopeStructure>
                <LocationOfData>Figure 2</LocationOfData>
                <EpitopeId>79836</EpitopeId>
                <ReferenceStartingPosition>23</ReferenceStartingPosition>
                <ReferenceEndingPosition>37</ReferenceEndingPosition>
                <EpitopeEvidenceCode>Representative selection</EpitopeEvidenceCode>
                <EpitopeStructureDefines>Exact Epitope</EpitopeStructureDefines>
                <Assays>
                    <MhcBinding>
                        <LocationOfData>Figures 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, Tables 1, 2 and PDB 1KLU</LocationOfData>
                        <MhcBindingId>1489401</MhcBindingId>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>175</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <QuantitativeMeasurement>1.93</QuantitativeMeasurement>
                            <MeasurementInequality>=</MeasurementInequality>
                            <AssayComments>The crystal structure contains the MHC/epitope complex bound to the superantigen (SAG) staphylococcal enterotoxin type C3, variant 3B2 (SEC3-3B2). SAG PDB chain is D.</AssayComments>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <MhcAlleleId>52</MhcAlleleId>
                        <ThreeDimensionalStructureOfComplex>
                            <ComplexPdbId>1KLU</ComplexPdbId>
                            <MhcChain1PdbChain>A</MhcChain1PdbChain>
                            <MhcChain2PdbChain>B</MhcChain2PdbChain>
                            <EpitopePdbChain>C</EpitopePdbChain>
                            <EpitopeResidues>C: G23, E24, L25, I26, G27, T28, L29, N30, A31, A32, K33, V34, P35, A36, D37;</EpitopeResidues>
                            <ViewerFlag>Y</ViewerFlag>
                            <Comments>[| P-3: G23; P-2: E24; P-1: L25; P1: I26; P2: G27; P3: I28; P4: L29; P5: N30; P6: A31; P7: A32; P8: K33; P9: V34; P10: P35; P11: A36; P12: D37; |]  The SAG molecule interacts with regions of the MHC α subunit and does not contact the epitope. As such, the binding of the SAG to the MHC/Epitope complex does not cause any conformational changes to the epitope structure. Only some information is given about MHC-Epitope interactions: Epitope residue P3: T28; makes extensive interactions with the MHC α subunit, including van der Waals interactions with A: Q9, F22, F54; and a water mediated hydrogen bonding network to A: E55. Conformational comparison between complexes SEC3-3B2/HLA-DR1 with TPI(wt), SEC3-3B2/HLA-DR1 with TPI(T28-&gt;I28) [PDB: 1KLG] and SEC3-3B2/HLA-DR1 with HA [unpublished data]: The first two structures are very similar. No significant differences were found between the two MHC molecules. The structures of the two epitopes are also very similar. Most differences are found at their N and C-terminal residues: P-3: G23; and P12: D37;. The only important difference between TPI(wt) and TPI(T28-&gt;I28) is at the side chain of P3: I28; in the mutant epitope, which is rotated relative to that of residue P3: T28; in the wild-type epitope. In all three structures, the epitopes have similar main-chain conformations, especially in the region spanning the epitope anchor residues P1, P4, P6, P7, P9. The only difference is that epitope HA binds to the MHC molecule with a slightly higher affinity than the other two. This is because of the different interactions the residues make at position P4. Specifically, residue P4: L29; in TPI makes three van der Waals interactions with residues from the MHC α-chain, whereas residue P4: T313; in HA, apart form these three van der Waals interactions, also makes a hydrogen bond with an MHC α-chain residue and water-mediated hydrogen bonds to two other MHC α-chain residues.</Comments>
                            <CuratedContacts>
                                <EpitopeResidues>C: G23, E24, L25, I26, G27, T28, L29, N30, A31, A32, K33, V34, P35, A36, D37;</EpitopeResidues>
                                <EpitopeResiduesInteractingWithMhc>C: ;</EpitopeResiduesInteractingWithMhc>
                                <MhcResiduesInteractingWithEpitope>A: ; B: ;</MhcResiduesInteractingWithEpitope>
                            </CuratedContacts>
                            <CalculatedContacts>
                                <EpitopeResiduesInteractingWithMhc>C: G23, E24, L25, I26, G27, T28, L29, N30, A31, A32, K33, V34, P35, D37</EpitopeResiduesInteractingWithMhc>
                                <MhcResiduesInteractingWithEpitope>A: Q9, F22, F24, F32, W43, F51, A52, S53, F54, E55, N62, V65, D66, A68, N69, I72, M73, K75; B: L11, F13, P56, D57, Y60, W61, R71, Y78, H81, N82, V85</MhcResiduesInteractingWithEpitope>
                                <ContactAreaForEpitope>1248.8</ContactAreaForEpitope>
                                <ContactAreaForMhc>937.9</ContactAreaForMhc>
                            </CalculatedContacts>
                        </ThreeDimensionalStructureOfComplex>
                    </MhcBinding>
                </Assays>
                <Assays>
                    <MhcBinding>
                        <LocationOfData>Table 3</LocationOfData>
                        <MhcBindingId>1907127</MhcBindingId>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>417</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <QuantitativeMeasurement>13.0</QuantitativeMeasurement>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <MhcAlleleId>52</MhcAlleleId>
                    </MhcBinding>
                </Assays>
            </Epitope>
            <Epitope>
                <EpitopeName>HA 306-318</EpitopeName>
                <EpitopeStructure>
                    <FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                        <ChemicalType>Peptide from protein</ChemicalType>
                        <LinearSequence>PKYVKQNTLKLAT</LinearSequence>
                        <StartingPosition>306</StartingPosition>
                        <EndingPosition>318</EndingPosition>
                        <SourceMolecule>
                            <GenBankId>1101228B</GenBankId>
                        </SourceMolecule>
                        <SourceOrganismId>11320</SourceOrganismId>
                    </FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                </EpitopeStructure>
                <LocationOfData>Reference cited</LocationOfData>
                <EpitopeId>48237</EpitopeId>
                <ReferenceStartingPosition>306</ReferenceStartingPosition>
                <ReferenceEndingPosition>318</ReferenceEndingPosition>
                <EpitopeEvidenceCode>Representative selection</EpitopeEvidenceCode>
                <EpitopeStructureDefines>Exact Epitope</EpitopeStructureDefines>
                <EpitopeComments>The epitope sequence is from the reference cited: Southwood et al. (1998) J Immunol 160: 3363-3373 [PMID: 9531296].</EpitopeComments>
                <Assays>
                    <MhcBinding>
                        <LocationOfData>Table 3</LocationOfData>
                        <MhcBindingId>1907129</MhcBindingId>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>417</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive-High</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <QuantitativeMeasurement>5.0</QuantitativeMeasurement>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <MhcAlleleId>52</MhcAlleleId>
                    </MhcBinding>
                </Assays>
            </Epitope>
        </Epitopes>
    </Reference>
</References>

