<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<References xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema http://beta.iedb.org/schema/Curation.xsd" xmlns="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <Reference>
        <ReferenceId>1332</ReferenceId>
        <DateLastUpdated>2020-09-10-07:00</DateLastUpdated>
        <Article>
            <PubmedId>12175336</PubmedId>
            <Abstract>Clostridium perfringens type E iota toxin consists of two unlinked proteins designated as iota a (Ia; molecular mass approximately 47 kDa), an ADP-ribosyltransferase and iota b (Ib; molecular mass approximately 81 kDa) which binds to the cell surface and facilitates Ia entry into the cytosol. By Western-blot analysis, Ib incubated with Vero cells at 37 degrees C generated a cell-associated, SDS-insoluble oligomer of Ib (molecular mass&gt;220 kDa) within 15 s, which was still evident 110 min after washing cells. Ib oligomerization was temperature, but not pH, dependent and was facilitated by a cell-surface protein(s). Within 5 min at 37 degrees C, cell-bound Ib generated Na(+)/K(+) permeable channels that were blocked by Ia. However, Ib-induced channels or oligomers were not formed at 4 degrees C. Two monoclonal antibodies raised against Ib that recognize unique, neutralizing epitopes within residues 632-655 either inhibited Ib binding to cells and/or oligomerization, unlike a non-neutralizing monoclonal antibody that binds within Ib residues 28-66. The Ib protoxin (molecular mass approximately 98 kDa), which does not facilitate iota cytotoxicity but binds to Vero cells, did not oligomerize or form ion-permeable channels on cells, and neither trypsin nor chymotrypsin treatment of cell-bound Ib protoxin induced large complex formation. The link between Ib oligomers and iota toxicity was also apparent with a resistant cell line (MRC-5), which bound to Ib with no evidence of oligomerization. Overall, these studies revealed that the biological activity of iota toxin is dependent on a long-lived, cell-associated Ib complex that rapidly forms ion-permeable channels in cell membranes. These results further reveal the similarities of C. perfringens iota toxin with other bacterial binary toxins produced by Bacillus anthracis and C. botulinum.</Abstract>
            <ArticleYear>2002</ArticleYear>
            <ArticlePages>801-8</ArticlePages>
            <ArticleTitle>Clostridium perfringens iota toxin: characterization of the cell-associated iota b complex.</ArticleTitle>
            <Authors>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Stiles</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Bradley G</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Hale</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Martha L</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Marvaud</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Jean Christophe</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Popoff</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Michel R</ForeName>
                </Author>
            </Authors>
            <Affiliations>Toxinology Division, Department of Immunology and Molecular Biology, U.S. Army Medical Research Institute of Infectious Diseases, Frederick, MD 21702-5011, USA. bradley.stiles@amedd.army.mil.</Affiliations>
            <ArticleChemicalList>Antibodies;Bacterial Toxins;Biopolymers;Enterotoxins;iota toxin, Clostridium perfringens;ADP Ribose Transferases</ArticleChemicalList>
            <ArticleMeshHeadingsList>ADP Ribose Transferases(immunology; metabolism; pharmacology); Animals; Antibodies(metabolism); Bacterial Toxins(immunology; metabolism; pharmacology); Biopolymers(metabolism); Cells, Cultured; Chlorocebus aethiops; Clostridium perfringens(metabolism); Enterotoxins(metabolism; pharmacology); Flow Cytometry; Humans; Hydrogen-Ion Concentration; Protein Binding; Temperature; Vero Cells</ArticleMeshHeadingsList>
            <Journal>
                <Volume>367</Volume>
                <Issue>Pt 3</Issue>
                <Title>The Biochemical journal</Title>
                <Issn>0264-6021</Issn>
                <MedlineTa>Biochem J</MedlineTa>
            </Journal>
        </Article>
        <Epitopes>
            <Epitope>
                <EpitopeStructure>
                    <FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                        <ChemicalType>Peptide from protein</ChemicalType>
                        <LinearSequence>SYFTSGENVMTYKKLRIYAVTPDN</LinearSequence>
                        <StartingPosition>843</StartingPosition>
                        <EndingPosition>866</EndingPosition>
                        <SourceMolecule>
                            <GenBankId>Q46221</GenBankId>
                        </SourceMolecule>
                        <SourceOrganismId>1502</SourceOrganismId>
                    </FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                </EpitopeStructure>
                <LocationOfData>Author's communication</LocationOfData>
                <EpitopeId>62548</EpitopeId>
                <ReferenceStartingPosition>632</ReferenceStartingPosition>
                <ReferenceEndingPosition>655</ReferenceEndingPosition>
                <EpitopeEvidenceCode>Not determined</EpitopeEvidenceCode>
                <EpitopeStructureDefines>Epitope containing region/antigenic site</EpitopeStructureDefines>
                <EpitopeComments>Epitopic region located at the C-terminal region of Iota b toxin, implicated in the inhibition of toxin activity my mAbs that recognize it. Epitope positions given in the manuscript correspond to the proteolytically-activated iota toxin b. The positions in the database entry correspond to the full precursor protein.</EpitopeComments>
                <Assays>
                    <BCell>
                        <LocationOfData>Table 1, figure 4</LocationOfData>
                        <BCellId>22167</BCellId>
                        <Immunization>
                            <HostOrganism>
                                <OrganismId>10090</OrganismId>
                            </HostOrganism>
                            <FirstInVivoProcess>
                                <InVivoProcessType>Administration in vivo</InVivoProcessType>
                                <ImmunogenObject>
                                    <EpitopeRelation>Source Antigen</EpitopeRelation>
                                    <Object>
                                        <AccessionSequenceMolecule>
                                            <ChemicalType>Protein</ChemicalType>
                                            <Molecule>
                                                <GenBankId>Q46221</GenBankId>
                                            </Molecule>
                                            <SourceOrganismId>1502</SourceOrganismId>
                                        </AccessionSequenceMolecule>
                                    </Object>
                                </ImmunogenObject>
                                <ImmunogenReferenceName>Iota toxin component Ib</ImmunogenReferenceName>
                                <ImmunogenEvidenceCode>Not determined</ImmunogenEvidenceCode>
                                <Adjuvant>Alum (Aluminum hydroxide gel)</Adjuvant>
                                <Route>Intraperitoneal (i.p.)</Route>
                                <DoseSchedule>2 doses of 10 μg</DoseSchedule>
                            </FirstInVivoProcess>
                            <ImmunizationComments>Immunization details were provided in a previous reference, PMID 11254604.</ImmunizationComments>
                        </Immunization>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>316</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <AssayComments>mAb 4F6, previously reported to bind this epitopic region and neutralize toxin cytotoxicity is able to inhibit Iota toxin binding to Vero cells, and the subsequent oligomerization of the toxin on the cells into a large m.w. complex is congruently diminished. Other mAb previously shown to inhibit cytotoxicity and to be directed to this same region (1D11) is unable to inhibit binding, but the oligomerization step is partially inhibited by it.</AssayComments>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <AssayedAntibody>
                            <AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>Monoclonal</AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>
                            <AssayedAntibodyName>4F6</AssayedAntibodyName>
                        </AssayedAntibody>
                        <Antigen>
                            <AntigenReferenceName>Iota toxin component Ib</AntigenReferenceName>
                            <AntigenConformation>Native</AntigenConformation>
                            <AntigenObject>
                                <EpitopeRelation>Source Antigen</EpitopeRelation>
                                <Object>
                                    <AccessionSequenceMolecule>
                                        <ChemicalType>Protein</ChemicalType>
                                        <Molecule>
                                            <GenBankId>Q46221</GenBankId>
                                        </Molecule>
                                        <SourceOrganismId>1502</SourceOrganismId>
                                    </AccessionSequenceMolecule>
                                </Object>
                            </AntigenObject>
                            <AntigenEvidenceCode>Not determined</AntigenEvidenceCode>
                        </Antigen>
                    </BCell>
                </Assays>
            </Epitope>
        </Epitopes>
    </Reference>
</References>

