<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<References xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema http://beta.iedb.org/schema/Curation.xsd" xmlns="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <Reference>
        <ReferenceId>1334</ReferenceId>
        <DateLastUpdated>2018-10-16-07:00</DateLastUpdated>
        <Article>
            <PubmedId>12149464</PubmedId>
            <Abstract>Mycobacterium tuberculosis and Mycobacterium bovis bacillus Calmette-Guérin produce a heparin-binding hemagglutinin adhesin (HBHA) required for extrapulmonary dissemination and a laminin-binding protein (LBP) involved in cytoadherence through laminin recognition. These adhesins bear posttranslational modifications that are not present when the proteins are produced in a recombinant (r) form in Escherichia coli. Mass spectrometry analysis of HBHA revealed that the posttranslational modifications are borne by the C-terminal moiety, which comprises the heparin-binding domain made of repeated lysine-rich motifs. Amino acid sequencing showed that these modifications consist of mono- and dimethyllysines within these motifs. The methyllysine-containing repeats were recognized by mAb 4057D2 and were also detected in LBP, which is equally recognized by mAb 4057D2. This Ab does not recognize the recombinant forms of these proteins. However, when rHBHA and rLBP were subjected to NaBH(4) and formalin treatment to induce lysine methylation, reactivity with mAb 4057D2 was recovered. Methylated rHBHA displayed enhanced resistance to proteolysis compared with rHBHA, as previously observed for native HBHA. S-adenosylmethionine-dependent HBHA methyltransferase activity was detected in the cell-wall fractions of M. bovis bacillus Calmette-Guérin and of Mycobacterium smegmatis, a species that produces LBP but naturally lacks hbhA, suggesting that the same enzyme(s) methylate(s) both LBP and HBHA. This hypothesis was confirmed by the fact that HBHA produced by recombinant M. smegmatis was also methylated. These results show that mycobacteria use enzymatic methylation of lysines to ensure greater stability of their adhesins.</Abstract>
            <ArticleYear>2002</ArticleYear>
            <ArticlePages>10759-64</ArticlePages>
            <ArticleTitle>Mycobacterial heparin-binding hemagglutinin and laminin-binding protein share antigenic methyllysines that confer resistance to proteolysis.</ArticleTitle>
            <Authors>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Pethe</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Kevin</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Bifani</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Pablo</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Drobecq</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Hervé</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Sergheraert</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Christian</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Debrie</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Anne-Sophie</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Locht</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Camille</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Menozzi</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Franco D</ForeName>
                </Author>
            </Authors>
            <Affiliations>Institut National de la Santé et de la Recherche Médicale U447, Lille Cedex, France.</Affiliations>
            <ArticleChemicalList>Adhesins, Bacterial;Antigens, Bacterial;Epitopes, B-Lymphocyte;Hemagglutinins;Lectins;Receptors, Laminin;heparin-binding hemagglutinin;Protein O-Methyltransferase;Serine Endopeptidases;glutamyl endopeptidase;Trypsin;Lysine</ArticleChemicalList>
            <ArticleMeshHeadingsList>Adhesins, Bacterial(immunology; metabolism); Animals; Antigens, Bacterial(immunology; metabolism); Binding Sites; Bronchoalveolar Lavage Fluid; Epitopes, B-Lymphocyte(immunology; metabolism); Hemagglutinins(immunology; metabolism); Lectins; Lysine(immunology; metabolism); Methylation; Mice; Mycobacterium bovis(metabolism); Mycobacterium smegmatis(metabolism); Mycobacterium tuberculosis(metabolism); Protein O-Methyltransferase(metabolism); Protein Processing, Post-Translational; Receptors, Laminin(metabolism); Serine Endopeptidases(metabolism); Trypsin(metabolism)</ArticleMeshHeadingsList>
            <Journal>
                <Volume>99</Volume>
                <Issue>16</Issue>
                <Title>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</Title>
                <Issn>0027-8424</Issn>
                <MedlineTa>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</MedlineTa>
            </Journal>
        </Article>
        <Epitopes>
            <Epitope>
                <EpitopeName>HBHA 159-199</EpitopeName>
                <EpitopeStructure>
                    <FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                        <ChemicalType>Peptide from protein</ChemicalType>
                        <LinearSequence>LPKKAAPAKKAAPAKKAAPAKKAAAKKAPAKKAAAKKVTQK</LinearSequence>
                        <ModifiedResidues>K4, K9, K10, K15, K16, K21, K22, K26, K27, K31, K32, K36, K37</ModifiedResidues>
                        <Modifications>Methylation|METH</Modifications>
                        <StartingPosition>159</StartingPosition>
                        <EndingPosition>199</EndingPosition>
                        <SourceMolecule>
                            <GenBankId>P0A5P6.2</GenBankId>
                        </SourceMolecule>
                        <SourceOrganismId>10000329</SourceOrganismId>
                    </FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                </EpitopeStructure>
                <LocationOfData>Fig 2</LocationOfData>
                <EpitopeId>38555</EpitopeId>
                <ReferenceStartingPosition>159</ReferenceStartingPosition>
                <ReferenceEndingPosition>199</ReferenceEndingPosition>
                <EpitopeEvidenceCode>Not determined</EpitopeEvidenceCode>
                <EpitopeStructureDefines>Epitope containing region/antigenic site</EpitopeStructureDefines>
                <EpitopeComments>C terminal domain of source protein (HBHA) shown to be methylated (either mono or dimethylated) in lysine residues at positions 162, 167, 168, 173, 174, 179, 180, 184, 185, 189, 190, 194 and 195 when extracted form Mycobacterium tuberculosis but not when expressed in E.coli. The methyllysines (confined to this region or HBHA) are involved in the recognition by a mAb that doesn’t recognize recombinant HBHA. The presence of these modified lysines is related to enhanced resistance to proteolysis. The presence of methyllysines is observed to mediate recognition by this mAb of another protein, Laminin binding protein (LBP) from Mycobacterium smegmatis.</EpitopeComments>
                <Assays>
                    <BCell>
                        <LocationOfData>Figure 4</LocationOfData>
                        <BCellId>21017</BCellId>
                        <Immunization>
                            <HostOrganism>
                                <OrganismId>10000000</OrganismId>
                            </HostOrganism>
                            <FirstInVivoProcess>
                                <InVivoProcessType>Administration in vivo</InVivoProcessType>
                                <ImmunogenObject>
                                    <EpitopeRelation>Taxonomic Sibling</EpitopeRelation>
                                    <Object>
                                        <Organism>
                                            <SubType>Organism</SubType>
                                            <SourceOrganismId>1764</SourceOrganismId>
                                        </Organism>
                                    </Object>
                                </ImmunogenObject>
                                <ImmunogenReferenceName>Mycobacterium avium</ImmunogenReferenceName>
                                <ImmunogenEvidenceCode>Not determined</ImmunogenEvidenceCode>
                                <Route>Intraperitoneal (i.p.)</Route>
                                <DoseSchedule>3 doses of 8 micrograms precipitate</DoseSchedule>
                            </FirstInVivoProcess>
                            <ImmunizationComments>Origin of mAb 4057D2 is detailed in previous reference (PMID 1713196)</ImmunizationComments>
                        </Immunization>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>37</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <AssayComments>Western-blot analysis of recombinant source protein (HBHA) purified from E.coli and subjected to chemical methylation shows that the methylated form is recognized by mAb 4057D2 (originally obtained against M. avium) as effectively as M.tuberculosis isolated source protein, while non-methylated recombinant protein is not recognized. Similar results are obtained when studying recombinant protein subjected to enzymatic methylation by M. bovis and M. smegmatis lysates (the latter lacking endogenous HBHA), where the methyltransferase activity is mainly in the cell wall fraction. M. smegmatis Laminin binding protein (LBP) is also recognized by this mAb, but not when expressed recombinantly in E. coli. This cross reactivity is dependent on the presence of methyl-lysines.</AssayComments>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <AssayedAntibody>
                            <AssayedAntibodySourceMaterial>Purified Immunoglobulin</AssayedAntibodySourceMaterial>
                            <AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>Monoclonal</AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>
                            <AssayedAntibodyName>4057D2</AssayedAntibodyName>
                            <AssayedAntibodyHeavyChainType>IgG3</AssayedAntibodyHeavyChainType>
                        </AssayedAntibody>
                        <Antigen>
                            <AntigenReferenceName>HBHA (Heparin-binding hemagglutinin Adhesin)</AntigenReferenceName>
                            <AntigenConformation>Non-Native/Unknown</AntigenConformation>
                            <AntigenObject>
                                <EpitopeRelation>Source Antigen</EpitopeRelation>
                                <Object>
                                    <AccessionSequenceMolecule>
                                        <ChemicalType>Protein</ChemicalType>
                                        <Molecule>
                                            <GenBankId>P0A5P6.2</GenBankId>
                                        </Molecule>
                                        <SourceOrganismId>10000329</SourceOrganismId>
                                    </AccessionSequenceMolecule>
                                </Object>
                            </AntigenObject>
                            <AntigenEvidenceCode>Not determined</AntigenEvidenceCode>
                        </Antigen>
                    </BCell>
                </Assays>
            </Epitope>
        </Epitopes>
    </Reference>
</References>

