<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<References xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema http://beta.iedb.org/schema/Curation.xsd" xmlns="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <Reference>
        <ReferenceId>1454</ReferenceId>
        <DateLastUpdated>2020-09-10-07:00</DateLastUpdated>
        <Article>
            <PubmedId>9692956</PubmedId>
            <Abstract>Antibody NC41 binds to the subtype N9 neuraminidase (NA) of influenza virus A/tern/Australia/ G70c/75 and inhibits its enzyme activity. To address the molecular mechanisms by which antibodies interact with neuraminidase and the requirements for successful escape from antibody inhibition, we made amino acid substitutions in heavy chain CDRs of NC41. Antibody proteins expressed as a single-chain Fv (scFv) fused with maltose-binding protein were assayed for binding to NA by ELISA. Association constants (Ka) for wild-type and mutant scFvs are as follows: wild type, 2 x 10(7) M-1; Asn31--&gt;Gln, 2 x 10(7) M-1; Glu96--&gt;Asp, 1 x 10(7) M-1; Asp97--&gt;Lys, 6 x 10(6) M-1; and Asn98--&gt;Gln, 8 x 10(6) M-1. The Ka for intact NC41 antibody was 4 x 10(8) M-1 in the same assay, reflecting increased stability compared to that of the scFv. Mutations in the scFv antibody had less of an effect on binding than mutations in their partners on the NA, and modeling studies suggest that interactions involving the mutant antibody side chains occur, even without taking increased flexibility into account. Asp97 forms a salt link with NA critical contact Lys434; of the four mutants, D97K shows the largest reduction in binding to NA. Mutant N98Q also shows reduced binding, most likely through the loss of interaction with NA residue Thr401. Substitution N31Q had no effect on Ka. NC41 residue Glu96 interacts with NA critical contact Ser368, yet E96D showed only a 2-fold reduction in binding to NA, apparently because the H bond can still form. Asp97 and Asn98 provide the most important interactions, but some binding is maintained when they are mutated, in contrast to their partners on the NA. The results are consistent with maturation of the immune response, when the protein epitope is fixed while variation in the antibody paratope allows increasing affinity. Influenza viruses may exploit this general mechanism since single amino acid changes in the epitope allow the virus to escape from the antibody.</Abstract>
            <ArticleYear>1998</ArticleYear>
            <ArticlePages>10660-70</ArticlePages>
            <ArticleTitle>Critical interactions in binding antibody NC41 to influenza N9 neuraminidase: amino acid contacts on the antibody heavy chain.</ArticleTitle>
            <Authors>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Pruett</LastName>
                    <ForeName>P S</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Air</LastName>
                    <ForeName>G M</ForeName>
                </Author>
            </Authors>
            <Affiliations>Department of Microbiology, University of Alabama at Birmingham 35294, USA.</Affiliations>
            <ArticleChemicalList>Amino Acids;Antibodies, Monoclonal;Immunoglobulin Fragments;Immunoglobulin Heavy Chains;Immunoglobulin Variable Region;Neuraminidase</ArticleChemicalList>
            <ArticleMeshHeadingsList>Amino Acid Sequence; Amino Acid Substitution(genetics); Amino Acids(genetics; immunology; metabolism); Animals; Antibodies, Monoclonal(biosynthesis; chemistry; metabolism); Base Sequence; Binding Sites, Antibody; Fluorescence Polarization; Immunoglobulin Fragments(biosynthesis; chemistry; metabolism); Immunoglobulin Heavy Chains(chemistry; genetics; metabolism); Immunoglobulin Variable Region(biosynthesis; chemistry; metabolism); Influenza A virus(immunology); Models, Molecular; Molecular Sequence Data; Mutagenesis, Site-Directed; Neuraminidase(chemistry; immunology; metabolism)</ArticleMeshHeadingsList>
            <Journal>
                <Volume>37</Volume>
                <Issue>30</Issue>
                <Title>Biochemistry</Title>
                <Issn>0006-2960</Issn>
                <MedlineTa>Biochemistry</MedlineTa>
            </Journal>
        </Article>
        <Epitopes>
            <Epitope>
                <EpitopeName>G70c NA</EpitopeName>
                <EpitopeStructure>
                    <DiscontinuousRegionOnAccessionSequenceMolecule>
                        <ChemicalType>Discontinuous protein residues</ChemicalType>
                        <DiscontinuousResidues>S368, S373, N400, T401, K434</DiscontinuousResidues>
                        <SourceMolecule>
                            <GenBankId>P03472.1</GenBankId>
                        </SourceMolecule>
                        <SourceOrganismId>155917</SourceOrganismId>
                    </DiscontinuousRegionOnAccessionSequenceMolecule>
                </EpitopeStructure>
                <LocationOfData>Figure 1</LocationOfData>
                <EpitopeId>77489</EpitopeId>
                <ReferenceRegion>S368, S373, N400, T401, K434</ReferenceRegion>
                <EpitopeEvidenceCode>Not determined</EpitopeEvidenceCode>
                <EpitopeStructureDefines>Partial Epitope</EpitopeStructureDefines>
                <EpitopeComments>Discontinuous epitope of Influenza A N9 neuraminidase (G70c NA) was deduced from interactions with antibody NC41 previously by Nuss JM et al. 1993;15:121-132.  Key residues involved in the antibody-peptide complex were identified in the current study: Ser368, Lys434, and Thr401.</EpitopeComments>
                <Assays>
                    <BCell>
                        <LocationOfData>Table 2</LocationOfData>
                        <BCellId>24488</BCellId>
                        <Immunization>
                            <HostOrganism>
                                <OrganismId>10090</OrganismId>
                            </HostOrganism>
                            <FirstInVivoProcess>
                                <InVivoProcessType>Unknown</InVivoProcessType>
                            </FirstInVivoProcess>
                            <ImmunizationComments>Monoclonal antibodies against Influenza A neuraminidase were generated from hybridomas provided by RG Webster and than purified either by dialysis or over a column.  No details of original hybridoma production provided.</ImmunizationComments>
                        </Immunization>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>253</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <QuantitativeMeasurement>499999998000</QuantitativeMeasurement>
                            <AssayComments>Binding curves for the interaction of G70c NA peptide with NC41 antibody (plus scFv wild type and mutants) were established.   Binding was presented as a percent of maximum (Figure 8).  Equilibrium constants (Ka) for the antibody-peptide complex were then either estimated from the binding curve or calculated using the binding equation: [bound NA]/[free NA][free Ab].  The Ka for the NC41 antibody binding to G70c NA was 5e&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;1/nM.  Ka for wild type and mutant  scFv fragments of NC41 were also tested.  Ka of these were considerably lower and therefore helped to identify critical interactive residues on the antibody: N31, E96, N98, D97.</AssayComments>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <AssayedAntibody>
                            <AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>Monoclonal</AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>
                            <AssayedAntibodyName>NC41</AssayedAntibodyName>
                        </AssayedAntibody>
                        <Antigen>
                            <AntigenReferenceName>Influenza A virus</AntigenReferenceName>
                            <AntigenConformation>Non-Native/Unknown</AntigenConformation>
                            <AntigenObject>
                                <EpitopeRelation>Source Organism</EpitopeRelation>
                                <Object>
                                    <Organism>
                                        <SubType>Organism</SubType>
                                        <SourceOrganismId>155917</SourceOrganismId>
                                    </Organism>
                                </Object>
                            </AntigenObject>
                            <AntigenEvidenceCode>Not determined</AntigenEvidenceCode>
                        </Antigen>
                    </BCell>
                </Assays>
                <Assays>
                    <BCell>
                        <LocationOfData>Figure 5</LocationOfData>
                        <BCellId>24487</BCellId>
                        <Immunization>
                            <HostOrganism>
                                <OrganismId>10090</OrganismId>
                            </HostOrganism>
                            <FirstInVivoProcess>
                                <InVivoProcessType>Unknown</InVivoProcessType>
                            </FirstInVivoProcess>
                            <ImmunizationComments>Monoclonal antibodies against Influenza A neuraminidase were generated from hybridomas provided by RG Webster and than purified either by dialysis or over a column.  No details of original hybridoma production provided.</ImmunizationComments>
                        </Immunization>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>277</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <QuantitativeMeasurement>120000004000</QuantitativeMeasurement>
                            <AssayComments>Fluorescence quenching was used to determine Ka of the interaction of G70c NA  with antibody NC41 or its Fab in solution phase.  Titration of G70c with NC41 yielded a Ka of 1.2e&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;/nM.  Ka was the same for the interaction of G70c peptide with the Fab fragment of NC41.  Ka was also measured for the interaction of G70c with scFv fragment, with and without, a fusion partner (MBP).  While scFv fragments (with or without single site-mutations in the heavy chain) could bind G70c, the interactions were much weaker than whole antibody (Figures 6 and 7) and helped define critical contacts on G70c NA peptide.</AssayComments>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <AssayedAntibody>
                            <AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>Monoclonal</AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>
                            <AssayedAntibodyName>NC41</AssayedAntibodyName>
                        </AssayedAntibody>
                        <Antigen>
                            <AntigenReferenceName>G70c NA</AntigenReferenceName>
                            <AntigenConformation>Non-Native/Unknown</AntigenConformation>
                            <AntigenObject>
                                <EpitopeRelation>Source Antigen</EpitopeRelation>
                                <Object>
                                    <AccessionSequenceMolecule>
                                        <ChemicalType>Protein</ChemicalType>
                                        <Molecule>
                                            <GenBankId>P03472.1</GenBankId>
                                        </Molecule>
                                        <SourceOrganismId>155917</SourceOrganismId>
                                    </AccessionSequenceMolecule>
                                </Object>
                            </AntigenObject>
                            <AntigenEvidenceCode>Not determined</AntigenEvidenceCode>
                        </Antigen>
                    </BCell>
                </Assays>
            </Epitope>
        </Epitopes>
    </Reference>
</References>

