<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<References xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema http://beta.iedb.org/schema/Curation.xsd" xmlns="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <Reference>
        <ReferenceId>577</ReferenceId>
        <DateLastUpdated>2020-09-10-07:00</DateLastUpdated>
        <Article>
            <PubmedId>15507295</PubmedId>
            <Abstract>INTRODUCTION: Antiphospholipid syndrome (APS) is a systemic autoimmune disease, associated not only with a hypercoagulable state and recurrent fetal loss but with many diverse clinical manifestations including heart involvement, neurological manifestations, as well as skin, kidney and hematologic abnormalities. Cardiac manifestations include coronary by-pass graft and angioplasty occlusions, cardiomyopathy, cyanotic congenital heart disease, intracardiac thrombus and complications of cardiovascular surgery. The valvular heart disease was defined as Libman-Sacks nonbacterial endocarditis. Previously, we have shown a linear subendothelial deposition of anti-cardiolipin/beta2 glycoprotein I (beta2GPI) antibodies in the valve specimens derived from APS patients. The involvement of complement C3c in the pathogenesis was documented. We assessed the beta2GPI-related target epitope recognized by the anti-beta2GPI Abs on the valves. MATERIALS AND METHODS: Antiphospholipid syndrome (APS) is a systemic autoimmune disease, associated not only with a hypercoagulable state and recurrent fetal loss but with many diverse clinical manifestations including heart involvement, neurological manifestations, as well as skin, kidney and hematologic abnormalities. Cardiac manifestations include coronary by-pass graft and angioplasty occlusions, cardiomyopathy, cyanotic congenital heart disease, intracardiac thrombus and complications of cardiovascular surgery. The valvular heart disease was defined as Libman-Sacks nonbacterial endocarditis. Previously, we have shown a linear subendothelial deposition of anti-cardiolipin/beta2 glycoprotein I (beta2GPI) antibodies in the valve specimens derived from APS patients. The involvement of complement C3c in the pathogenesis was documented. We assessed the beta2GPI-related target epitope recognized by the anti-beta2GPI Abs on the valves.In order to find the beta2GPI-related target epitopes recognized by the anti-beta2GPI antibodies on the valves, we used beta2GPI-related synthetic peptides. The presence of anti-beta2GPI Abs on the studied valves was detected by anti-idiotypic antibody, followed by immunoperoxidase analysis. Biotin attached to the N-terminal of beta2GPI-related synthetic peptides and control peptide were used to identify the epitope addressed by the anti-beta2GPI Abs deposited on the patient's valve. The binding was probed by streptavidin-peroxidase and appropriate substrate. The specificity was confirmed by competition assays with control peptide and anti-idiotypic antibody. RESULTS: Antiphospholipid syndrome (APS) is a systemic autoimmune disease, associated not only with a hypercoagulable state and recurrent fetal loss but with many diverse clinical manifestations including heart involvement, neurological manifestations, as well as skin, kidney and hematologic abnormalities. Cardiac manifestations include coronary by-pass graft and angioplasty occlusions, cardiomyopathy, cyanotic congenital heart disease, intracardiac thrombus and complications of cardiovascular surgery. The valvular heart disease was defined as Libman-Sacks nonbacterial endocarditis. Previously, we have shown a linear subendothelial deposition of anti-cardiolipin/beta2 glycoprotein I (beta2GPI) antibodies in the valve specimens derived from APS patients. The involvement of complement C3c in the pathogenesis was documented. We assessed the beta2GPI-related target epitope recognized by the anti-beta2GPI Abs on the valves.In order to find the beta2GPI-related target epitopes recognized by the anti-beta2GPI antibodies on the valves, we used beta2GPI-related synthetic peptides. The presence of anti-beta2GPI Abs on the studied valves was detected by anti-idiotypic antibody, followed by immunoperoxidase analysis. Biotin attached to the N-terminal of beta2GPI-related synthetic peptides and control peptide were used to identify the ...</Abstract>
            <ArticleYear>2004</ArticleYear>
            <ArticlePages>589-92</ArticlePages>
            <ArticleTitle>Libman-Sacks endocarditis associated with antiphospholipid syndrome and infection.</ArticleTitle>
            <Authors>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Blank</LastName>
                    <ForeName>M</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Shani</LastName>
                    <ForeName>A</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Goldberg</LastName>
                    <ForeName>I</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Kopolovic</LastName>
                    <ForeName>J</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Amigo</LastName>
                    <ForeName>M C</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Magrini</LastName>
                    <ForeName>L</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Shoenfeld</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Y</ForeName>
                </Author>
            </Authors>
            <Affiliations>Department of Medicine B, The Center for Autoimmune Diseases, Sheba Medical Center, Tel-Hashomer 52621, Israel.</Affiliations>
            <ArticleChemicalList>Antibodies, Anticardiolipin;Epitopes;Glycoproteins;Peptides;beta 2-Glycoprotein I</ArticleChemicalList>
            <ArticleMeshHeadingsList>Antibodies, Anticardiolipin(chemistry); Antiphospholipid Syndrome(complications; immunology); Endocarditis(complications; immunology); Epitopes(chemistry); Glycoproteins(immunology); Heart Valves(metabolism); Humans; Infections(complications); Lupus Erythematosus, Systemic(immunology); Peptides(chemistry); Protein Binding; beta 2-Glycoprotein I</ArticleMeshHeadingsList>
            <Journal>
                <Volume>114</Volume>
                <Issue>5-6</Issue>
                <Title>Thrombosis research</Title>
                <Issn>1879-2472</Issn>
                <MedlineTa>Thromb Res</MedlineTa>
            </Journal>
        </Article>
        <Epitopes>
            <Epitope>
                <EpitopeStructure>
                    <FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                        <ChemicalType>Peptide from protein</ChemicalType>
                        <LinearSequence>TLRVYK</LinearSequence>
                        <StartingPosition>152</StartingPosition>
                        <EndingPosition>157</EndingPosition>
                        <SourceMolecule>
                            <GenBankId>P02749.3</GenBankId>
                        </SourceMolecule>
                        <SourceOrganismId>9606</SourceOrganismId>
                    </FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                </EpitopeStructure>
                <LocationOfData>Page 590</LocationOfData>
                <EpitopeId>65050</EpitopeId>
                <ReferenceStartingPosition>152</ReferenceStartingPosition>
                <ReferenceEndingPosition>157</ReferenceEndingPosition>
                <EpitopeEvidenceCode>Not determined</EpitopeEvidenceCode>
                <EpitopeStructureDefines>Exact Epitope</EpitopeStructureDefines>
                <Assays>
                    <BCell>
                        <LocationOfData>Figures 1 and 2</LocationOfData>
                        <BCellId>5087</BCellId>
                        <Immunization>
                            <HostOrganism>
                                <OrganismId>9606</OrganismId>
                            </HostOrganism>
                            <FirstInVivoProcess>
                                <InVivoProcessType>Occurrence of autoimmune disease</InVivoProcessType>
                                <DiseaseState>DOID:10314</DiseaseState>
                                <DiseaseStage>Chronic</DiseaseStage>
                            </FirstInVivoProcess>
                            <ImmunizationComments>Antiphospholipid syndrome (APS) related Libman-Sacks endocarditis patient's valves were tested.</ImmunizationComments>
                        </Immunization>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>38</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <AssayComments>The epitopic peptide bounf the anti-β2GPI Abs deposited on the patient's valve. The specificity was confirmed by competition assays with anti-idiotypic antibody.</AssayComments>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <AssayedAntibody>
                            <AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>Polyclonal</AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>
                            <AssayedAntibodyName>anti-β2GPI antibody</AssayedAntibodyName>
                        </AssayedAntibody>
                        <Antigen>
                            <AntigenConformation>Non-Native/Unknown</AntigenConformation>
                            <AntigenObject>
                                <EpitopeRelation>Epitope</EpitopeRelation>
                                <Object>
                                    <FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                                        <ChemicalType>Peptide from protein</ChemicalType>
                                        <LinearSequence>TLRVYK</LinearSequence>
                                        <StartingPosition>152</StartingPosition>
                                        <EndingPosition>157</EndingPosition>
                                        <SourceMolecule>
                                            <GenBankId>P02749.3</GenBankId>
                                        </SourceMolecule>
                                        <SourceOrganismId>9606</SourceOrganismId>
                                    </FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                                </Object>
                            </AntigenObject>
                            <AntigenEvidenceCode>Exact match to reference information</AntigenEvidenceCode>
                        </Antigen>
                    </BCell>
                </Assays>
            </Epitope>
        </Epitopes>
    </Reference>
</References>

