<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<References xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema http://beta.iedb.org/schema/Curation.xsd" xmlns="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <Reference>
        <ReferenceId>872</ReferenceId>
        <DateLastUpdated>2019-06-04-07:00</DateLastUpdated>
        <Article>
            <PubmedId>11900844</PubmedId>
            <Abstract>Truncated NS3 proteins, expressed by recombinant baculoviruses, were used to investigate the location of conserved B-cell epitopes on this non-structural bovine viral diarrhoea virus (BVDV) protein. A goat anti-pestivirus antiserum, and a panel of anti-NS3 monoclonal antibodies, including the BVDV-1 specific antibody P1D8, were used to verify the presence or absence of the epitopes. Interestingly, the monoclonal antibodies reacted only with the truncated protein encompassing the helicase domain of NS3. Expression of the B-cell epitopes was dependent on, but not within, a 57 amino acid sequence at the carboxy-terminal end of this protein, supporting observations that these conserved epitopes are conformational in nature. A comparison of deduced amino acid sequences of the helicase domain from BVDV-1, BVDV-2, BDV and CSFV isolates highlighted a single amino acid that appeared to be unique to P1D8-reactive BVDV-1 isolates. Site-directed mutagenesis studies confirmed that this amino acid is critical for the expression of the BVDV-1 specific NS3 epitope recognised by the P1D8 monoclonal antibody. Surprisingly, the amino acid was also important for an epitope recognised by two group-specific monoclonal antibodies, P1H11 and P4A11. Protein modelling studies, based on the structure of the hepatitis C NS3 helicase domain, indicated that this amino acid occupies a prominent position on the surface of the protein.</Abstract>
            <ArticleYear>2002</ArticleYear>
            <ArticlePages>111-24</ArticlePages>
            <ArticleTitle>A single amino acid is critical for the expression of B-cell epitopes on the helicase domain of the pestivirus NS3 protein.</ArticleTitle>
            <Authors>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Brown</LastName>
                    <ForeName>L M</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Papa</LastName>
                    <ForeName>R A</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Frost</LastName>
                    <ForeName>M J</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Mackintosh</LastName>
                    <ForeName>S G</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Gu</LastName>
                    <ForeName>X</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Dixon</LastName>
                    <ForeName>R J</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Shannon</LastName>
                    <ForeName>A D</ForeName>
                </Author>
            </Authors>
            <Affiliations>Department of Biological Sciences, University of Western Sydney, Macarthur, P.O. Box 555, Campbelltown, NSW 2560, Australia. louise.brown@agric.nsw.gov.au.</Affiliations>
            <ArticleChemicalList>DNA, Viral;Epitopes, B-Lymphocyte;NS3 protein, flavivirus;Viral Nonstructural Proteins;Serine Endopeptidases;RNA Helicases</ArticleChemicalList>
            <ArticleMeshHeadingsList>Amino Acid Substitution; Animals; Baculoviridae(genetics); Base Sequence; Cattle; Classical Swine Fever Virus(genetics; isolation &amp; purification); DNA, Viral; Diarrhea Viruses, Bovine Viral(genetics; immunology; isolation &amp; purification); Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay(methods); Epitope Mapping; Epitopes, B-Lymphocyte(chemistry; genetics; immunology); Gene Expression; Genetic Vectors(genetics); Goats; Immunoenzyme Techniques; Models, Molecular; Molecular Sequence Data; Protein Structure, Tertiary; RNA Helicases(chemistry; genetics; immunology); Recombination, Genetic; Serine Endopeptidases; Staining and Labeling(methods); Swine; Viral Nonstructural Proteins(chemistry; genetics; immunology)</ArticleMeshHeadingsList>
            <Journal>
                <Volume>84</Volume>
                <Issue>1-2</Issue>
                <Title>Virus research</Title>
                <Issn>1872-7492</Issn>
                <MedlineTa>Virus Res</MedlineTa>
            </Journal>
        </Article>
        <Epitopes>
            <Epitope>
                <EpitopeName>L1858</EpitopeName>
                <EpitopeStructure>
                    <DiscontinuousRegionOnAccessionSequenceMolecule>
                        <ChemicalType>Discontinuous protein residues</ChemicalType>
                        <DiscontinuousResidues>L271</DiscontinuousResidues>
                        <SourceMolecule>
                            <GenBankId>AAC08532.1</GenBankId>
                        </SourceMolecule>
                        <SourceOrganismId>158474</SourceOrganismId>
                    </DiscontinuousRegionOnAccessionSequenceMolecule>
                </EpitopeStructure>
                <LocationOfData>Table 5</LocationOfData>
                <EpitopeId>77002</EpitopeId>
                <ReferenceRegion>L1858</ReferenceRegion>
                <EpitopeEvidenceCode>Not determined</EpitopeEvidenceCode>
                <EpitopeStructureDefines>Partial Epitope</EpitopeStructureDefines>
                <EpitopeComments>As the title of this article states, this Leucine1858 residue is critical for recognition of BVDV-1 isolates by mAb P1D8. Position is relative to SD-1 polyprotein. Genbank accesion is for virus polyprotien.</EpitopeComments>
                <Assays>
                    <BCell>
                        <LocationOfData>Table 6</LocationOfData>
                        <BCellId>14923</BCellId>
                        <Immunization>
                            <HostOrganism>
                                <OrganismId>10000000</OrganismId>
                            </HostOrganism>
                            <FirstInVivoProcess>
                                <InVivoProcessType>Administration in vivo</InVivoProcessType>
                                <ImmunogenObject>
                                    <EpitopeRelation>Source Organism</EpitopeRelation>
                                    <Object>
                                        <Organism>
                                            <SubType>Organism</SubType>
                                            <SourceOrganismId>158474</SourceOrganismId>
                                        </Organism>
                                    </Object>
                                </ImmunogenObject>
                                <ImmunogenEvidenceCode>Not determined</ImmunogenEvidenceCode>
                            </FirstInVivoProcess>
                            <ImmunizationComments>Immunization was performed over a 6-12 month period, with a mixture of five different BVDV isolates (Oregon C24V reference strain and 4 isolates from New South Wales, Australia). NS-1 myeloma cells were used as fusion partner for hybridoma production.</ImmunizationComments>
                        </Immunization>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>34</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <AssayComments>Binding by monoclonal antibodies P1D8, P1H11 and P4A11 to recombinant source protein is abolished if aa 1858 is a Valine or a Serine (Hay and NZ 97-360 strains) and when that residue is mutated to Leucine, as in the Trangie strain, reactivity is recovered. mAb P1D8 is specific for all BVDV-1 isolates where aa1858 is a Leucine (i.e. except for Hay and NZ 97-360 strains). The reactivity of  P1H11 and P4A11, pestivirus specific antibodies, is also dependent on this aa in BVDV-1 isolates, but not in BVDV-2, BDV or CSFV isolates. That aa lateral chain is shown in protein modeling analysis to protrude on the surface of the protein.</AssayComments>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <AssayedAntibody>
                            <AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>Monoclonal</AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>
                            <AssayedAntibodyName>P1D8</AssayedAntibodyName>
                        </AssayedAntibody>
                        <Antigen>
                            <AntigenReferenceName>NS3</AntigenReferenceName>
                            <AntigenConformation>Non-Native/Unknown</AntigenConformation>
                            <AntigenObject>
                                <EpitopeRelation>Source Antigen</EpitopeRelation>
                                <Object>
                                    <AccessionSequenceMolecule>
                                        <ChemicalType>Protein</ChemicalType>
                                        <Molecule>
                                            <GenBankId>AAC08532.1</GenBankId>
                                        </Molecule>
                                        <SourceOrganismId>158474</SourceOrganismId>
                                    </AccessionSequenceMolecule>
                                </Object>
                            </AntigenObject>
                            <AntigenEvidenceCode>Not determined</AntigenEvidenceCode>
                        </Antigen>
                    </BCell>
                </Assays>
            </Epitope>
        </Epitopes>
    </Reference>
</References>

