<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<References xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema http://beta.iedb.org/schema/Curation.xsd" xmlns="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <Reference>
        <ReferenceId>908</ReferenceId>
        <DateLastUpdated>2020-09-10-07:00</DateLastUpdated>
        <Article>
            <PubmedId>10736175</PubmedId>
            <Abstract>Peptide binding reactions of class II MHC proteins exhibit unusual kinetics, with extremely slow apparent rate constants for the overall association (&lt;100 M(-)(1) s(-)(1)) and dissociation (&lt;10(-)(5) s(-)(1)) processes. Various linear and branched pathways have been proposed to account for these data. Using fluorescence resonance energy transfer between tryptophan residues in the MHC peptide binding site and aminocoumarin-labeled peptides, we measured real-time kinetics of peptide binding to empty class II MHC proteins. Our experiments identified an obligate intermediate in the binding reaction. The observed kinetics were consistent with a binding mechanism that involves an initial bimolecular binding step followed by a slow unimolecular conformational change. The same mechanism is observed for different peptide antigens. In addition, we noted a reversible inactivation of the empty MHC protein that competes with productive binding. The implications of this kinetic mechanism for intracellular antigen presentation pathways are discussed.</Abstract>
            <ArticleYear>2000</ArticleYear>
            <ArticlePages>3751-62</ArticlePages>
            <ArticleTitle>A three-step kinetic mechanism for peptide binding to MHC class II proteins.</ArticleTitle>
            <Authors>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Joshi</LastName>
                    <ForeName>R V</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Zarutskie</LastName>
                    <ForeName>J A</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Stern</LastName>
                    <ForeName>L J</ForeName>
                </Author>
            </Authors>
            <Affiliations>Department of Chemistry, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Massachusetts 02139, USA.</Affiliations>
            <ArticleChemicalList>Antigens, Differentiation, B-Lymphocyte;HLA-DR1 Antigen;Hemagglutinin Glycoproteins, Influenza Virus;Histocompatibility Antigens Class II;Oligopeptides;invariant chain</ArticleChemicalList>
            <ArticleMeshHeadingsList>Antigens, Differentiation, B-Lymphocyte(chemistry; genetics; metabolism); Energy Transfer; Escherichia coli(genetics); Genetic Vectors(chemistry; metabolism); HLA-DR1 Antigen(chemistry; genetics; metabolism); Hemagglutinin Glycoproteins, Influenza Virus(chemistry; genetics; metabolism); Histocompatibility Antigens Class II(chemistry; genetics; metabolism); Humans; Kinetics; Models, Chemical; Oligopeptides(chemistry; genetics; metabolism); Protein Binding(genetics); Spectrometry, Fluorescence</ArticleMeshHeadingsList>
            <Journal>
                <Volume>39</Volume>
                <Issue>13</Issue>
                <Title>Biochemistry</Title>
                <Issn>0006-2960</Issn>
                <MedlineTa>Biochemistry</MedlineTa>
            </Journal>
        </Article>
        <Epitopes>
            <Epitope>
                <EpitopeName>HA</EpitopeName>
                <EpitopeStructure>
                    <SequenceMoleculeNoNaturalSource>
                        <ChemicalType>Peptide, no natural source</ChemicalType>
                        <LinearSequence>PRFVKQNTLRLAT</LinearSequence>
                        <ModifiedResidues>P1</ModifiedResidues>
                        <Modifications>Acetylation|ACET</Modifications>
                    </SequenceMoleculeNoNaturalSource>
                </EpitopeStructure>
                <EpitopeRelatedObject>
                    <RelatedObjectType>The epitope is an analog of:</RelatedObjectType>
                    <RelatedObject>
                        <FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                            <ChemicalType>Peptide from protein</ChemicalType>
                            <LinearSequence>PRYVKQNTLKLAT</LinearSequence>
                            <StartingPosition>306</StartingPosition>
                            <EndingPosition>318</EndingPosition>
                            <SourceMolecule>
                                <GenBankId>P12589.1</GenBankId>
                            </SourceMolecule>
                            <SourceOrganismId>383571</SourceOrganismId>
                        </FragmentOfANaturalSequenceMolecule>
                    </RelatedObject>
                </EpitopeRelatedObject>
                <LocationOfData>Page 3752</LocationOfData>
                <EpitopeId>49185</EpitopeId>
                <EpitopeStructureDefines>Epitope containing region/antigenic site</EpitopeStructureDefines>
                <EpitopeComments>AMCA conjugation was performed on K5 to study binding kinetics to MHC II.  The synthesized peptide has substituted residues from natural sequence (PRYVKQNTLKLAT)  to facilitate labeling and FRET analysis. Swiss-prot ID and positions provided correspond to one of sequenced hemmaglutinins, from a source species strain were the natural sequence of epitope is found.  Epitope PRFVKQNTLRLAT is an analog of peptide PRYVKQNTLKLAT from the hemagglutinin protein of influenza A virus (A/Memphis/6/86).</EpitopeComments>
                <Assays>
                    <MhcBinding>
                        <LocationOfData>Table 2</LocationOfData>
                        <MhcBindingId>15599</MhcBindingId>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>278</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <AssayComments>FRET analysis of binding and dissociation reactions allows for the analysis of reactant concentration dependence of the kinetic constants. The detailed analysis of the reactions both kinetically and at equilibrium show that there is a fast first step of association (k-1/k1 ~ 10^8M) of the intermediate complex followed by a slower (k forward ~ 10^-4 s^-1) conformational rearrangement to yield the final peptide-MHC complex. Also, less than 10% of MHC molecules are shown to be active when derived both from insect an E. coli cells, and a slow MHC activation step (kact ~10^-5 s^-1) is necessary to provide the reactant molecule. Similar results and kinetic constants are obtained with the peptide CLIP from the Ia associated invariant chain.</AssayComments>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <MhcAlleleId>327</MhcAlleleId>
                    </MhcBinding>
                </Assays>
            </Epitope>
            <Epitope>
                <EpitopeName>CLIP</EpitopeName>
                <EpitopeStructure>
                    <SequenceMoleculeNoNaturalSource>
                        <ChemicalType>Peptide, no natural source</ChemicalType>
                        <LinearSequence>VSRMRMATPLLMQ</LinearSequence>
                        <ModifiedResidues>V1,L11</ModifiedResidues>
                        <Modifications>Main chain modification</Modifications>
                    </SequenceMoleculeNoNaturalSource>
                </EpitopeStructure>
                <LocationOfData>Figure 1</LocationOfData>
                <EpitopeId>71100</EpitopeId>
                <EpitopeStructureDefines>Exact Epitope</EpitopeStructureDefines>
                <EpitopeComments>The synthesized peptide has substituted residues form natural sequence (VSKMRMATPLLMQ)  to facilitate labeling and FRET analysis of binding kinetics to MHC II. AMCA conjugation was performed on position 11 (γ), where naturally occurring L was substituted with 2,4-diaminobutyric acid. Also K3 in the natural sequence was modified to R to avoid multiple labeling. A.k.a HLA class II histocompatibility antigen, gamma chain; HLA-DR antigens associated invariant chain; p33; and CD74 antigen.Epitope VSRMRMATPLÎ³MQ is an analog of peptide VSKMRMATPLLMQ from human HLA gamma chain.</EpitopeComments>
                <Assays>
                    <MhcBinding>
                        <LocationOfData>Table 2</LocationOfData>
                        <MhcBindingId>15609</MhcBindingId>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>278</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <AssayComments>FRET analysis of binding and dissociation reactions allows for the analysis of reactant concentration dependence of the kinetic constants. The detailed analysis of the reactions both kinetically and at equilibrium show that there is a fast first step of association (k-1/k1 ~ 10^8M) of the intermediate complex followed by a slower (k forward ~ 10^-4 s^-1) conformational rearrangement to yield the final peptide-MHC complex. Also, less than 10% of MHC molecules are shown to be active when derived both from insect an E. coli cells, and a slow MHC activation step (kact ~10^-5 s^-1) is necessary to provide the reactant molecule. Similar results and kinetic constants are obtained with a influenza HA peptide.</AssayComments>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <MhcAlleleId>327</MhcAlleleId>
                    </MhcBinding>
                </Assays>
            </Epitope>
        </Epitopes>
    </Reference>
</References>

