<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<References xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema http://beta.iedb.org/schema/Curation.xsd" xmlns="http://www.iedb.org/schema/CurationSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <Reference>
        <ReferenceId>947</ReferenceId>
        <DateLastUpdated>2020-09-10-07:00</DateLastUpdated>
        <Article>
            <PubmedId>12222931</PubmedId>
            <Abstract>We investigated a virus-neutralizing conformational epitope of the rabies virus glycoprotein (G) that is recognized by an anti-G monoclonal antibody (mAb; #1-46-12) and shared by most of the laboratory strains of the virus. To investigate the epitope structure, we isolated escape mutants from the HEP-Flury virus (wild-type; wt) after repeated passages in culture in the presence of the mAb. Immunofluorescence studies indicated that the mutants could be classified into two groups; the Group I lacked the epitope, while Group II preserved the epitope. The latter was dominant under the passage conditions, since Group I disappeared during the continuous passages. G proteins showed different electrophoretic mobilities; G protein of Group I migrated at the same rate as wt G protein, while that of Group II migrated at a slower rate, which was shown to be due to acquisition of an additional oligosaccharide side chain. Nucleotide sequencing of the G gene strongly suggested that amino acid substitutions at Thr-36 by Pro and Ser-39 by Thr of the G protein are responsible for the escape mutations of Groups I and II, respectively. The latter is a unique mutation of the rabies virus that allows the G protein to be glycosylated additionally at Asn-37, a potential glycosylation site that is not glycosylated in the parent virus, in preserving the epitope-positive conformation. These results suggest that to keep the 1-46-12 epitope structure is of greater survival advantage for the virus to escape the neutralization than to destroy it, which could be achieved by acquiring an additional oligosaccharide chain at Asn-37.</Abstract>
            <ArticleYear>2002</ArticleYear>
            <ArticlePages>449-61</ArticlePages>
            <ArticleTitle>Studies on the escape mutants of rabies virus which are resistant to neutralization by a highly conserved conformational epitope-specific monoclonal antibody #1-46-12.</ArticleTitle>
            <Authors>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Irie</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Takashi</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Matsuda</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Yukihiro</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Honda</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Yoshikazu</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Morimoto</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Kinjiro</ForeName>
                </Author>
                <Author>
                    <LastName>Kawai</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Akihiko</ForeName>
                </Author>
            </Authors>
            <Affiliations>Department of Molecular Microbiology, Graduate School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan.</Affiliations>
            <ArticleChemicalList>Antibodies, Monoclonal;Antibodies, Viral;Antigens, Viral;Epitopes;Glycoproteins;Viral Envelope Proteins;glycoprotein G, Rabies virus</ArticleChemicalList>
            <ArticleMeshHeadingsList>Amino Acid Sequence; Animals; Antibodies, Monoclonal(immunology); Antibodies, Viral(immunology); Antigens, Viral(chemistry; immunology); Base Sequence; Cells, Cultured; Electrophoresis, Polyacrylamide Gel(methods); Epitopes(chemistry; immunology); Evolution, Molecular; Fluorescent Antibody Technique; Glycoproteins(chemistry; genetics; immunology); Models, Genetic; Molecular Sequence Data; Mutagenesis, Site-Directed; Mutation; Neutralization Tests; Protein Conformation; Rabies(immunology); Viral Envelope Proteins(chemistry; genetics; immunology)</ArticleMeshHeadingsList>
            <Journal>
                <Volume>46</Volume>
                <Issue>7</Issue>
                <Title>Microbiology and immunology</Title>
                <Issn>0385-5600</Issn>
                <MedlineTa>Microbiol Immunol</MedlineTa>
            </Journal>
        </Article>
        <Epitopes>
            <Epitope>
                <EpitopeName>Antigenic Site III epitope</EpitopeName>
                <EpitopeStructure>
                    <DiscontinuousRegionOnAccessionSequenceMolecule>
                        <ChemicalType>Discontinuous protein residues</ChemicalType>
                        <DiscontinuousResidues>T55</DiscontinuousResidues>
                        <SourceMolecule>
                            <GenBankId>P19462.1</GenBankId>
                        </SourceMolecule>
                        <SourceOrganismId>11296</SourceOrganismId>
                    </DiscontinuousRegionOnAccessionSequenceMolecule>
                </EpitopeStructure>
                <LocationOfData>Introduction, Abstract,</LocationOfData>
                <EpitopeId>77405</EpitopeId>
                <ReferenceRegion>T36</ReferenceRegion>
                <EpitopeEvidenceCode>Not determined</EpitopeEvidenceCode>
                <EpitopeStructureDefines>Partial Epitope</EpitopeStructureDefines>
                <EpitopeComments>Conformational epitope was determined from sequencing of viral escape mutants of rabies virus after multiple passages using mAb #1-46-12.</EpitopeComments>
                <Assays>
                    <BCell>
                        <LocationOfData>Figure 2</LocationOfData>
                        <BCellId>11400</BCellId>
                        <Immunization>
                            <HostOrganism>
                                <OrganismId>10090</OrganismId>
                            </HostOrganism>
                            <FirstInVivoProcess>
                                <InVivoProcessType>Unknown</InVivoProcessType>
                            </FirstInVivoProcess>
                        </Immunization>
                        <AssayInformation>
                            <AssayTypeId>37</AssayTypeId>
                            <QualitativeMeasurement>Positive</QualitativeMeasurement>
                            <AssayComments>The mAb bound to wild type rabies virus spike glycoprotein.  Polyclonal sera against virus nucleoprotein was used as a positive control. These data were compared to mAb and polyclonal Ab binding to viral escape mutants.</AssayComments>
                        </AssayInformation>
                        <AssayedAntibody>
                            <AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>Monoclonal</AssayedAntibodyPurificationStatus>
                            <AssayedAntibodyName>mAb #1-46-12</AssayedAntibodyName>
                            <AssayedAntibodyHeavyChainType>IgG2a</AssayedAntibodyHeavyChainType>
                        </AssayedAntibody>
                        <Antigen>
                            <AntigenReferenceName>Rabies virus</AntigenReferenceName>
                            <AntigenConformation>Non-Native/Unknown</AntigenConformation>
                            <AntigenObject>
                                <EpitopeRelation>Source Organism</EpitopeRelation>
                                <Object>
                                    <Organism>
                                        <SubType>Organism</SubType>
                                        <SourceOrganismId>11296</SourceOrganismId>
                                    </Organism>
                                </Object>
                            </AntigenObject>
                            <AntigenEvidenceCode>Not determined</AntigenEvidenceCode>
                        </Antigen>
                    </BCell>
                </Assays>
            </Epitope>
        </Epitopes>
    </Reference>
</References>

